Music.
Can you hear me now?
Good morning.
By name.
Okay.
Well, I'd like to welcome all of you, not just those who welcome me by name, but thank
you.
I'd like to welcome all of you to this, our second week in the money series.
And for those of you who just felt the room kind of go down and are asking yourselves
if you're new or if you missed last week, if you're wondering why we're talking about
money instead of something spiritual, I would say to you that it's true that our priorities
and our outlook in money matters brightly reflect and are strongly influenced by our orientation
and our focus and maturity in spiritual matters.
One reflects the other clearly, one drives the other clearly.
And for those of you who've been around church for a while, you know, that's reflected.
I think Ryan said it last week in the common statement that Christ talked more about money
matters than any other topic.
If you've probably heard that.
Yes.
Okay.
And for you, I would say that is true.
Christ did talk about money a lot.
And it's important that we understand why he's talking about money and what he's talking
about when he talks about money, because he also talked about farming and fishing a lot.
And we should not take from that that he particularly cares about how we farm and fish or if we're
farmers and fishermen.
We should take from that that he was talking to farmers and fishermen, right?
And he was speaking in terms that they would understand, speaking their language to speak
to them about spiritual matters and how they should live their life in response to those
spiritual truths, right?
So when we hear Christ talking about money a lot, I would say to you, what we should take
from that is that he talks so much about money to help us realize, or at least we should
realize how very focused on money we are, maybe more than him, how much he needs to speak in
those terms in order to get our attention and to address our affections.
Because, of course, much of our attention is expended in seeking to gather and maximize
wealth.
We convert our skills and resources, any opportunities that become available to us, we want to turn
those into some kind of liquid asset that we need for flourishing today and dealing with
that crisis we fear is going to happen tomorrow, right?
We call that temporary storehouse of wealth money, and it's a primary preoccupation of both survival
and flourishing for most of us.
Unfortunate part of this is that absorbed in my pursuit of money, my family needs that money
for today, and I fear we'll need even more tomorrow because I'm obliged to make comparisons
and trade-offs in value.
How much am I willing to give up of my time to get my children the thing that I'm pretty sure
will give them the opportunities that they need?
How much of my possessions am I willing to forego so that we can have the health care I think
we might need tomorrow, right?
And these trade-offs in value become a measurement of our life.
We have to have some method for making that trade-off.
We make that evaluation in money, and imperceptibly, it becomes not just a measurement of our value,
but a ruler of what we value.
So sometimes when Christ talks about money, he is using it as an analogy to teach us some
other truth, like he does with farming or fishing.
And sometimes when he's talking about money, as in the story we're going to deal with today,
he's talking to us about what we value and what he values, knowing that in some degree,
the answer that we give him would be in terms of money.
That's the language we're going to speak in when he says, what do you value?
His frequent references to money then, just to repeat it, may reflect our intense interest
in the subject more than his, right?
It's a subject then that we need to find his perspective on.
What's the angle that he sees these money questions from?
And we'd like to find that today as we look through the story of the rich young ruler.
So turn with me, if you will, to Mark 10.
It's going to be up on the screens.
The rich young ruler is a story that's repeated in all three of the synoptic Gospels, Matthew, Mark, and Luke.
We're going to read it today out of Mark.
In Mark 10 then, as he, Jesus, was setting out on a journey, a man ran up to him and knelt before him
and asked him, good teacher, what shall I do to inherit eternal life?
And Jesus said to him, why do you call me good?
I mean, no one's good except God alone.
You know the commandments.
Don't murder.
Don't commit adultery.
Don't steal.
Don't bear false witness.
Don't defraud, which means don't commit fraud.
Honor your father and mother.
And he said to Jesus, teacher, I've kept all these things from my youth up.
And looking up at him, Jesus felt a love for him.
And he said to him, one thing you lack, go and sell all you possess and give it to the poor
and you'll have treasure in heaven.
And come, follow me.
But at these words, he was saddened and he went away grieving for he was one who owned much property.
It's a very sad story.
The whole room got very quiet.
That's a story that's in all three synoptic Gospels.
It's one that I can tell the room's not wholly, you know, comfortable with.
And it's one that all three authors felt was absolutely core to explaining who Jesus was and what he taught, right?
When we see a story that's repeated in all three Gospels,
if you don't know, the three synoptic Gospels present the story of who Jesus was and what he taught to different audiences.
And so as a result, they will emphasize different points.
They'll bring up different stories sometimes that are more relevant to their audience to make a point.
Or they'll use wording that, you know, brings out certain details more because they're trying to convey who Jesus was to a new set of people.
And we've collected all three of these in the Bible.
So when you see a story that's in all three, it's important to know that's a core one, right?
Everybody who hung out with Jesus for the three years he was going around teaching recognized that without this story,
you couldn't really convey to everyone what Jesus said and who he was.
So this is a core piece.
So when you find those, it's important to see what's the same in all three and what's different, right?
So that you can see what's emphasized to those audiences.
The thing that's the same is that this story and its surrounding facts are very, very similar in all three.
They keep almost the same wording because this was such a core moment.
And we need to ask ourselves why the people who hung out with Jesus thought,
if you're going to understand him, you need to know this story, right?
And then there's small things that are different.
One thing that's different in that story of the rich young ruler that I just read,
did anyone hear the mention of youth or ruling?
No, you didn't.
There's none.
It's not mentioned there.
It's just a rich guy came up to Jesus.
In Matthew, which was written to a Jewish audience who had Jewish inheritance laws,
Matthew, just to add a little color to the story,
when he refers the pronoun, he refers to the young man, he says,
young man, which is the only way we know it was a young man.
And that would have been relevant to the Jewish audience
because a young man who had inherited already and had that much wealth
would have had a different outlook on life.
And it's significant then that he's asking Jesus,
how do I inherit into the kingdom of God, right?
Because he's a young man, that means he's just inherited into his family.
And he's trying to provide for his family.
And he's trying to make sure that they can get into the next step.
How can they get into the kingdom of heaven?
How can they inherit eternal life?
So he's not just thinking about himself.
That's just a little color that Matthew throws in for his audience.
Luke was writing to people in Rome, the elite of the empire,
who were pretty sure that there's nothing significant going on down in Judea.
No one there is significant in any of the stories that they would read in the Bible.
As a result, Luke needs to express that this guy coming up to Jesus was a significant person
so that the Romans can understand that when Jesus sort of sends him away
and tells him, you're not ready to follow me until you do these things,
that they understand that it was an odd and surprising thing that Christ did.
And so they say, Luke adds, this young man was a ruler.
And when he says ruler, he doesn't mean a governor or king.
He means a community leader, right?
That's the context it's set in.
So we get from what Matthew said and what Luke said,
that this man, this wealthy man, is at a young age,
a possessor now of the family fortune,
and he's risen to some prominence probably in the synagogue.
He's one of the local leaders in his community.
And as such, he would have had responsibility for those around him.
He would have had significance to how he laid out his money.
And so Christ telling him to sell all you have and give it to the poor,
is Christ asking him in his mind, at least,
and somewhat in reality, to dispossess his family, right?
He's asking him to get rid of the money you're planning to use
to take care of the family that you're caring for.
So that's not a simple thing that he's asking him to do.
So the young man, the one thing that is recorded in all three Gospels
is that the young man walked away sad and that he was a rich man.
That's the important bit that all three harp on, right?
It's a rich guy, he's taking care of these, and he walked away sad.
Why was he sad?
Had he lost anything?
Does he have to give away his money that he's worried about?
No, he's not lost his money.
Why is he sad?
Well, because he finds that he can't inherit in the kingdom
and he's disappointed by how he was addressed by this rabbi.
He comes up and he says,
good teacher, how, what must I do to inherit eternal life?
And as he says that, there's an inherent link he's created already
baked into his question that I think goodness is going to be tied to inheritance.
If I'm good enough, I should be qualified to inherit.
So the good teacher, and Christ sees that instantly, and he says to him, he addresses that instantly
by saying, why are you calling me good?
He calls him out, giving him the opportunity to say, there's none good but God, is what Jesus
says to him.
So that's giving the rich young ruler the opportunity to either say, oh, well, then you must be God,
or to say, oh, I understand it's not about goodness, right?
Either way, he could have gotten that.
But what he actually got from it was he was told not to say good teacher, so he doesn't.
When he addresses him the second time, he just says, well, teacher, right?
Which is what we get from this is the young man was very, he was a good student.
He paid attention.
He was trying to do what he was told to do.
And Christ saw this in him.
So he has addressed him and said, have you followed the commandments?
And does he list all 10 commandments?
He does not.
He lists five or six of them, depending on which Matthew, Mark, or Luke you're looking at.
And he lists the ones out there that are about how you treat your neighbor, right?
Don't murder, don't commit adultery, don't steal, don't lie about him in court, don't commit
fraud, honor your father and mother, that's six.
So these are the ones that he's asking him, when he said, how am I to inherit in the kingdom
of God?
How do I get eternal life?
Christ said, how are you treating your neighbor, right?
And tellingly, in Matthew, he also adds one more that wouldn't have made sense to the Roman
audiences, so it makes sense that that was omitted from the Mark and Luke list.
But in Matthew, it also says, love your neighbor as yourself.
So I'm willing to believe that he had not murdered anyone, given the benefit of the doubt, that
he hasn't committed adultery, he hasn't committed fraud.
When he says, I've done all things for my youth up, that seems reasonable.
It's possible, though, that Christ is pushing him a little further in trying to get him to
say, how do you treat those, your neighbors in society?
And we know from elsewhere that Christ believes the first and greatest commandment is Deuteronomy
6, love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind, and strength, and love your neighbor
as yourself, he says, is the second commandment, and much like the first.
So loving your God and loving your neighbor are closely tied, but loving your neighbor comes
from Leviticus 19.
It's this, if you go look it up, it's a laundry list, just sort of a scattershot of seemingly
disparate commandments, just in a list.
And it should have, it would have struck many people at the time as odd that Christ would
have pulled just one of those out as the second and greatest commandment.
But in Leviticus 19, it begins, you shall be holy for I, the Lord God, am holy.
So this is a list of how to be holy, how to be set apart for God's purposes.
And it starts, if you look at the theme, you read the list a few times, you'll see what
it is, is a list of how to be kind to those, how to be neighborly to those, how to be, it
says, godly to those, how to be holy around those that culture doesn't value.
So it begins the list with the first thing, leave your gleaning for the poor and unprotected
when you're farming and you drop something.
You have to leave it there for the poor people to pick up, right?
God's saying, that's how you become holy.
I am the Lord, your God.
It goes on to say, don't swear my name, don't swear falsely, don't sort of lie and say that
God's on your side.
Don't rob your neighbor, pay your laborers as soon as you can.
If you have day laborers working for you that are working hand to mouth, you pay them immediately.
You don't kind of keep the interest on the money and pay them when it's convenient for you.
You look out for those who need the money now.
I am the Lord.
Don't mistreat the disabled.
Don't show partiality in your judgment, meaning don't find court judgments that the rich and
influential can make happen to the detriment of those who don't have that kind of influence.
I am the Lord.
And in the middle of all this, you shall love your neighbor as yourself, which is the definition
of what all these are.
The redefinition is, who's your neighbor?
It's the guy that you're not considering valuable, right?
It's the poor guy who can't, it's the day laborer.
He goes on to say, don't molest or explore the vulnerable women around you.
Stand before the aged and honor them, including it by implication, not just your parents, but
any aged person that you might not think highly of.
Treat the immigrants in your community as natives.
You shall love him as yourself, for I am the Lord.
When you're treating your neighbor as yourself, that means the immigrant who has come in and
has, in your opinion, no natural rights to your community.
You shall love him as you love yourself.
Treat him as your neighbor, for I am the Lord.
Use accurate weights and balances.
So this is what Christ is challenging the rich young ruler to.
Have you loved your neighbor as yourself?
And when I say neighbor, I mean the people you're living with that you don't pay attention
to, the ones that you don't value.
I want you to change who you value.
You're focused on your family and your inheritance.
How to get a new inheritance of the kingdom of God to help them out.
I'm saying, are you taking care of the beggar?
That's proof that you value.
That's what I need in the kingdom of God.
And then the rich young ruler goes away saddened because he has much property.
When Christ, before he says this to him, it says he looks at him and he feels love for
him.
That word love is agape love.
That's the divine love of God.
And it means that when Christ throws this question at him, he's not trying to call him
out publicly.
He's not trying to ridicule him.
He's seen in him that there's potential here.
He's somebody he wants to reach out to.
And the only way he can reach him is to get him to reconsider, as the question says, what
is it he values?
I need you to value things as I do.
And he tells him four things, right?
He says, sell all your possessions, give them to the poor, get treasure in heaven, follow
me.
But I think the young man stopped listening after the first one, sell all your possessions,
right?
Which is unfortunate because Christ, he's not telling him to take his money and burn it,
He's not saying, get rid of your possession.
He's not saying what you lack is poverty.
He's not saying, he didn't even say, take your money and give it to your younger brother.
Let him take care of the family.
I need you to follow me, right?
What he said was, you have to change who you value.
You have to change what you value.
I need you to sell all you possess and give it to those that you currently don't value.
The problem was not having great wealth.
The problem was serving his wealth, allowing it to define his values and priorities.
When we, as head of households, balance living by faith with our responsibility for those
in our care, this is a problem that I'm guessing some of the people in the room identify with.
It feels difficult.
Do I, you know, do I live by faith or do I plan for tomorrow?
Do I just say God's going to take care of it or do I put a retirement plan in place?
You know, you feel like those are in conflict, but you feel like that, I would say, and because
I've seen this in my life, you feel like that when you somehow believe that the opportunities
that give you that finance and the money that you're planning on for tomorrow was somehow
created by and brought into place by you, right?
And you think it's somehow going to be the key to avoiding a million things you cannot control
in tomorrow.
So you have to ask yourself, are you being prideful in your assessment of yourself as the head
of household, as being the provider?
Are you being fearful in your assessment of what's going to have to take care of tomorrow
in your pride?
And I've found that in my experience, the conflict over faith versus responsibility just melts
away when my attitude is corrected.
It's like looking at the two faces and you see a candlestick.
You're looking at the same facts.
But when I recognize with great gratitude what has been given to me, and one of the key things
that's been given to me is the opportunity to provide for others made in God's image using
the resources he's handed to me.
The blessings that come down to you are so that you can hand them to others.
And when I recognize that, when I have that right perspective on who provided the wealth
and these opportunities that I'm stewarding, I find that conflict doesn't actually exist.
It's all in my prideful head.
So if you're asking yourself when you read this story, what's supposed to happen with my money
or how much do I have to give away, those aren't the right questions, right?
We probably established that by now.
You should be asking yourself, what is Christ trying to teach the rich young ruler, the young
man, and by proxy, me.
Let's just read a little more of the story because I think part of the problem is we stopped too
soon.
In all three Gospels, honestly, that story we just read, which has very real things to be
learned from it, that's just the setup.
I think if just that had happened, it wouldn't have been included in all three Gospels.
The conversation Jesus had with his disciples after, that was the epiphany moment.
So let's read what they say.
Jesus then, so the rich young ruler has walked away, he's not around anymore, and Jesus looks
around back at his disciples and says to them, how hard it will be for those who are wealthy
to enter the kingdom of God, in verse 23.
And the disciples were amazed by this.
But Jesus answered them again and said, children, how hard it is to enter the kingdom of God.
It's easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the
kingdom of God.
And they were even more astonished when he had said this.
And they responded then, who can be saved then?
And looking at them, Jesus said, well, with people it's impossible, but with God, it's not
with God, for all things are possible with God.
Well, it makes life easier.
It does.
It opens doors.
I've been recently trying to get, you know, my third child into college, and with more money,
he could go to a better college.
You know, he would have what I perceive to be better opportunities in the future.
But Christ is saying here, there are some doors that money will not open, and that should
be a relief to us.
He's saying, actually, there's one door here that it's actually maybe not even open to the
wealthy.
And as I say that, I think that there's probably in many of us a thing that just says, well,
I'm not wealthy.
This isn't talking to me, right?
Because wealth is always relative.
You might feel abashed when you read this, and you're worried about your own finances,
but you're probably imagining those slightly or much more affluent than yourselves as them
being the truly and difficultly wealthy persons this story is addressing.
And first of all, I just want to level set.
By virtue of living in America in the 20th century, we're more wealthy than the vast majority
of the people in Jesus that he was talking to that day, okay?
So this is talking to us just on a straightforward basis.
But whether you're worrying about getting enough EBT into your SNAP account, which some of us
are, or whether you're worried about how to get more EFTs into your brokerage account, which
some of us are, if you're fixated on those accounts and those financial transfers, improving
your tomorrow and solving your problems, this is the story that's addressing you.
It doesn't matter the volume of money.
It matters on your dependence on it.
And the fact that you would begin analyzing, which almost all of us did, your own level
of wealth as you hear this story, rather than the mechanism you use for assigning value,
that suggests that you are to some degree in the problem category of the person that this
story is written for.
Christ is not anti-wealth.
He's challenging this young man in the story who's limited by his attachment to wealth.
But the fact that you and I feel a slight little lightning of the chest and a little relief when
I say Christ isn't anti-wealth, that's a warning signal that we need to openly assess our own
hearts and realign the affections of our hearts and the methods of valuation that we use.
Because this is a story about idolatry and repentance from idolatry.
In Alistair's Begg words, he says, repentance is turning away from that which is emblematic of
our covetous heart.
That is repentance.
And we're always called to repent and believe the good news.
Repentance is turning away from the thing that we believe will save us tomorrow, right?
Back to God.
To repent is to turn away, leave the old way.
And that's what Christ called all the disciples to do.
Peter, John, they left their nets and followed him.
Matthew left the tax table and followed him when Christ called him.
He's calling this young man to do exactly what he called his other disciples to do.
Leave the thing that you're clinging to, believing it'll help you tomorrow, and make your tomorrow
sure, and follow me.
He told them, leave your money.
Give it to the poor so that you now have a new value assignment.
This will give you treasure in heaven.
Come follow me.
As Tim Keller said, anything you think can give you life, give your life power and joy
without God, that becomes a monster in your life.
So Christ isn't criticizing the rich.
He's critiquing those who value rich people, who value the richness, who think, are willing
to follow that monster of what Ryan referred to as mammon, the idea that the money you can
trust in for tomorrow will save you.
He's challenging them.
So what this young man lacks isn't poverty.
It's treasure in heaven.
And Christ told us, don't lay up for yourself treasure in heaven, where moss and rust corrupts,
but lay up for yourself treasure.
Don't lay up for yourself treasure on earth, where moss and rust corrupts, but lay up for
yourself treasure in heaven.
For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also, which is almost a self-defined term.
Of course, where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
That's the definition of treasure.
It's the thing that you guard.
It's the thing that your heart is set on.
And he's trying to tell you, it's not valuable inherently.
It's valuable because you've set your life on it, right?
Where your treasure is, there will your heart be also.
It's where is your heart?
That's what you're calling treasure.
I'm telling you, there's treasure in heaven.
And that's where your heart should be set.
We can't serve God and mammon.
You'll either love the one and despise the other, cling to the one, not the other.
You can't serve God and mammon.
And so, this is idolatry, which requires repentance.
And we have to recognize when we read this story that Christ doesn't sometimes tell people
you need to repent from your sins and sometimes tell people you need to give up your money.
He's telling this young man, your reliance on money is your sin.
You need to repent, leave that and follow me.
Stop following your reliance on money.
Follow me.
And this is very clear to us because in verse 23, 24, 25, he ends them with all the focus
isn't on the money.
Its focus is on the kingdom of heaven.
How hard it is for a man, a wealthy man to enter the kingdom of heaven.
And then in verse 25, at the end of 24, when the disciples are amazed that he said that, he
says, children, how hard it is to enter the kingdom of God, right?
It's not about rich people getting in.
It's anybody getting in, right?
How hard it is to enter the kingdom of God.
How hard is it?
He says at the end of 27, it's impossible.
So if you've heard a sermon that says, tries to explain how a camel sometimes kind of can,
but with humility, get through a gate that was called the eye of the needle, that's not
wrong, but it's not Jesus' point.
Jesus says it's impossible.
I use this analogy to tell you, you can't do it.
But with God, all things are possible.
Are you following the money?
Well, you can't get into heaven that way.
You're following Jesus.
Well, you can.
And why then, the important question is, in verse 26 and 27, the disciples were even more
astonished and they said, well, then who can be saved?
Isn't that an odd reaction?
I mean, if somebody today said, you know, rich people can't get to heaven, there'd be a chorus
of, woo, we're poor.
We have heaven to ourselves, you know.
But that's not the disciples' reaction.
They didn't say, hey, well, you know, we followed you.
We don't have any money.
We're good, right?
They were shocked.
The reason this story is in all the Gospels is because it presented a truth for the first
time, at least the first time they heard it, that we kind of grew up with.
We've heard this camel of the eye of the needle thing our whole lives.
It's kind of a cultural norm that you can decide to accept or not, but you know Jesus said
it.
They'd never heard that before.
This is the moment when it became, when this idea was revealed to them that the rich guy
wasn't better than they were because he was rich.
It never occurred to them.
They were shocked by the idea.
If he can't get into heaven, I know I can't get into heaven, right?
If he can't get into the kingdom of God, there's no way I can get into the kingdom of God.
Why is that?
Because they believed that wealth equals blessings.
They'd read the entire Old Testament, and wealth was frequently a sign of God's blessing.
And they did the connection.
Wealth comes from blessing.
Blessing is given to those who are righteous.
Righteous comes from my behavior.
Therefore, if God blesses me, I am more worthy.
And that's the bit where they go wrong, right?
Just because God blesses you doesn't make you more worthy.
We as head of households who are given a blessing and opportunity and wealth to care for others,
that doesn't make us more worthy.
It gives us more opportunities to mess up.
It gives us more opportunities to get it right and to care for those who are made in the image of God
that we're not valuing properly right now.
That's what this story is telling us.
And in all three of the synoptic Gospels, this is the key moment of epiphany for the apostles,
where they say, then who can be saved?
They're having to learn that blessing is just given by God.
It's not deserved.
And it's definitely not a marker of your value.
And Peter, he starts to get it.
Like, it's pretty cool that Peter's the first one to get it.
And he's like, oh, I got it.
In verse 28, Peter then says, it says Peter says, but I get the sense that he jumped up.
It's like, oh my goodness, right?
Behold, we've left everything to follow you, right?
Very exciting.
Wait a minute.
Does that mean I'm ahead of that guy and I'm getting into heaven, getting the kingdom of God?
I've left everything.
I'm totally poor.
I'm following you everywhere.
I think I'm building a kingdom of treasure in heaven.
Does that mean I get inheritance in the kingdom of heaven?
Is this working for me?
And Jesus answers him in verse 29, truly I say to you, there is no one who has left his
house or his brothers or his sister or his mother or his father, clearly addressing the
inheritance issue we talked about with the rich young ruler, for my sake and the gospel
sake.
But he will receive a hundred times as much now in the present age and houses and brothers
and sisters and mothers and children and farms.
And what he's talking about there is what we talked about in the Ephesians series.
Please go back and watch it if you haven't.
This idea of joining into the koinonia, the shared endeavor of the church that they had.
You have hundreds of brothers and sisters around you and they gave everything they had to take
care of each other's financial need, right?
You have the cattle on a thousand hills are mine, says Christ, right?
Or God and the prophecy and the full wealth of my kingdom is now at your disposal and all
the children who have been adopted as sons are with you.
You've inherited into this great kingdom.
And oh, by the way, Peter, in verse 30, along with that will come persecution.
And in the age to come, eternal life.
It's this whole package deal that's got nothing to do with the things you're valuing.
Yeah, there's, I mean, there'll be enough money.
You'll have your daily bread.
You have a wealthy father who cares for you, but it's a whole package deal.
Verse 31, but many who are first will be last and the last first.
That is truly an odd thing to end this section with.
Why would Jesus end it with that?
And why would it be so significant that all the gospel writers keep that, right?
That's the exclamation point at the end.
It's at least in part pointing to the rich young ruler.
I mean, the rich young ruler, everyone had assumed he was first and they just learned he
won't be first.
He's in the back of the line.
And they had assumed they were in the back of the line, but now they have hopes of being
first suddenly.
But it goes deeper than that because as soon as they've gotten to that point of, ooh, do
I get to be first?
All these other stories Jesus was telling them are falling into place.
And we know that because the rich young ruler is actually a story in the middle of a bunch
of other stories.
And you can see it most clearly in Matthew, but Mark and Luke do it as well.
So I'm going to talk about Matthew a little bit here.
But starting back in Matthew 18, which is two chapters earlier, the disciples are arguing.
About who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?
What is my position in the kingdom of heaven?
What's my rank?
And following that is story after story after story, just like that list in Leviticus of
Jesus showing how the people that they don't value have great value.
He talks about being kind to the children who are too vulnerable and can't take care of themselves.
Anyone who doesn't should have a millstone thrown around his neck, right?
Not being a stumbling block to those who don't quite understand yet.
Being very careful of their understanding and their beliefs.
Not being condescending to those who are lesser than you in your humble opinion.
He talks about the shepherd who has 99 sheep safe, but leaves them to go out and find the
one that's vulnerable and scared and unsecure out in the storm, right?
He talks about children again at the beginning of Matthew 19 saying, the disciples are trying
to keep children away from Jesus so he had time to deal with the important and valuable people.
And Christ said, forbid them not for theirs of the kingdom of heaven.
Unless you're like a little child, you can't get to the kingdom of heaven.
And then in the midst of all these stories that Luke, Matthew, Mark clearly have remembered,
these stories that talk about how to revalue the person that you weren't clearly valuing,
then is the story of the rich young ruler right in the middle of those.
And here's a guy that you think you should value.
And you learned from Christ, no, you shouldn't.
Because the camel can't go through the eye of the needle.
The disciples say, well, then who can be saved?
My whole worldview has just been blown up.
And the answer was, those who repent of their idolatry and follow me.
Get treasure in heaven.
Leave your money to those who I value and come follow me.
So the larger answer, following me, that isn't the final state.
It's a process.
And the disciples who just thought they had an epiphany and understood are now at the beginning of the learning process.
It's like getting your black belt and then you find out you have years of work ahead of you.
It began with who's the greatest and it ends with the last will be first and the first will be last.
Followed by the story, this parable Jesus gives of laborers who get unequal wages.
Very briefly, there's a man who owns a vineyard.
He needs to bring in the harvest.
He hires some day laborers, gives them a flat rate.
I'm going to give you this money to work in my vineyard all day.
And they do it.
At noon, he wants to make sure he gets the harvest in.
So he brings in more laborers, gives them the same flat rate so that now they're getting essentially twice as much per hour.
To do the same work because he wants to get the harvest in.
At the end of the day, with an hour left, he brings in more laborers, gives them the same flat rate, right?
So that at the end of the day, some of the laborers are complaining.
How come they got paid more?
Am I less valuable?
Who here is of the greatest?
And if you're one of the disciples and hadn't gotten that he's talking about you,
we see from its placement in this series of stories that eventually they did get it.
And they understood that this was a question about how do you value yourself?
And the parable is telling you, you're not valued by the labor you put in.
He gave you your daily bread.
I always give you your daily bread.
I make sure you're provided for.
What matters is that the harvest gets pulled in.
What's valuable is the harvest.
The reason you're in the kingdom of heaven, the reason we have this mission in common,
is that you're out bringing in the harvest.
Everything in the middle of who's the greatest in the kingdom in that parable is the disciples' memory of the things that Jesus had done and said that changed their conception of how to assign value.
So what does God value?
Well, Donovan read it this morning.
Matthew 6, 28, consider the lilies of the field.
They don't sow or reap, but Solomon closed them greater than Solomon, the richest king ever.
Hebrews says, keep your lives free from the love of money and be content with what you have, like the laborers in God's vineyard.
Because God has said, I will never leave you.
I will never forsake you.
If we listen to this story of the rich young ruler to find out how much money makes us acceptable to God,
or how much we can have and still have God accessible to us,
we've missed the revelation that money is not the water that God swims in.
Money is my mechanism for storing and trading value,
and it becomes quickly my mechanism for assigning value to the world around me.
But how can such a man as that draw close to the things of God?
With man, it's impossible, but with God, all things are possible.
The early church embodied this understanding in their practice of koinonia.
They're sharing all things in common.
And Barnabas was a type of the rich young ruler.
He was a wealthy man, a young wealthy man,
who sold his land and followed Jesus.
It says in Acts 4.32,
And the congregation of those who believed at the time,
just after the spirit fell on them at Pentecost,
were of one heart and one soul.
And not one of them claimed anything belonged to him, was his own.
But all things were common property in the koinonia.
And with great power,
the apostles were giving testimony to the resurrection of the Lord Jesus.
And the abundant grace was upon them all.
For there was not a needy person among them.
For all who were owners of land or houses would sell them and bring the proceeds to the sales.
They were doing what he'd asked the rich young ruler to do.
And they laid them at the apostles' feet,
who would then redistribute them to each as they had need.
Now, Joseph, a Levite of Cyprian birth,
who was also called Barnabas by the apostles,
which means son of encouragement,
he owned a tract of land and he sold it.
And he brought the money and laid it at the apostles' feet.
We know that Barnabas was from a wealthy family.
We know he didn't have to do this.
And we know that if he hadn't done this,
we would never have heard of him.
Barnabas was a guy who decided to put the kingdom of heaven ahead of his own plans for his future.
And what he ended up doing was becoming committed to Christ,
following him with his whole heart,
so that when Paul had met Christ and had gone out into the desert to try to figure out what to do with his life,
it was Barnabas that went out and got him and brought him back and put him into action.
He rehabilitated Paul.
And when John Mark left the mission field and went back in despair,
it was Barnabas that went and got John Mark and rehabilitated him.
John Mark wrote the story we just read.
We would never have known about it if Barnabas hadn't done what the story said.
Paul wrote most of the New Testament.
And both of those people were only there because Barnabas did what he asked the rich young ruler to do.
So we actually see it in action.
Their finances, the early church's finances and their devotions to the kingdom,
were all held together in one common endeavor, which they called Koinonia.
And in 1 Corinthians 10, 14, Paul says,
Therefore, my friends, flee from idolatry.
Leave your money behind and follow Christ.
It's your love of money.
It's not the cup of thanksgiving for which we give thanks, Koinonia, and the blood of Christ.
Suddenly he's talking about communion.
What we hold together is Christ's sacrifice.
And it's not the bread that we take, a Koinonia, and the body of Christ.
Because there's one loaf.
And we who are many are one body, for we all share that one loaf.
They saw their efforts and their money and Christ's sacrifice and their part in his sacrifice that they were willing to take part in.
All is one giant thing held in common in which they had shares.
And that's what Barnabas got into when he sold his land.
We're going to take communion this morning because we still today are part of that communion.
Still, over time and space, we've committed to that same long-term kingdom of God.
If you don't have your communion cup, this would be a great moment to go grab it.
We practice open communion here.
If you are committed to the kingdom of God and following Christ, we're glad to have you take communion with us.
Taking part in Christ's sacrifice and claiming a part in the new covenant.
Taking part in the endeavor we share together.
That is all part of the Koinonia.
So we do this with consideration in prayer.
We do not take it unworthily.
And we invite you with due consideration to take communion with us today as I read Paul's words.
That he received from the Lord what he passed on to us.
That the Lord Jesus, on the night he was betrayed, took bread.
And when he had given thanks for it, he broke it and said,
This is my body, which is for you.
Take this in remembrance of me.
And in the same way, after supper, he took the cup saying,
This cup is the new covenant in my blood.
Do this whenever you drink it in remembrance of me.
For whenever you eat this bread and drink this cup,
you proclaim the Lord's death until he comes.
Lord Father God, thank you this morning for what you've given us.
The opportunities that you've given us to share others.
The responsibilities you've given us from which we can learn a tiniest slip of what it's like to be you.
To take care of others made in your image.
For those this morning that struggle from hand to mouth.
That struggle to take care of multiple children on a shoestring budget.
I pray that you would help them find the joy in your provision for them.
And a release from the strain and the fear of tomorrow.
And for those of us who have put so much effort into trying to build for tomorrow.
That it's become a fixation for us.
I pray that you would help us find the joy of your provision.
And let go of our pride in which we believe we've done for ourselves.
And that you would help us see the value in those around us.
Including our own family.
The value they have before your kingdom.
As part of your design.
And that we would seek first the kingdom of God and your righteousness.
So that all the other things that we need will be added to us by your gracious kindness.
And we would recognize it for that when it happens.
Thank you.
In Jesus name.
Amen.
So may the peace of God which us surpasses all understanding guard your hearts and minds in Christ Jesus.
Go with God and we'll see you here next week.
Thank you very much.
I don't know what it's like to be.
I don't know what it's like to be you.
You don't know what it's like to be me.
What if we're all the same in different kinds of ways.
Can you, can you relate?
Have you ever been left when you should have been loved?
Has there ever been a time when you stayed but you should have run?
Cause I've been real, I've been faking.
Been a sinner, been a saint.
I've been right, I've been so, so wrong.
Yeah, I've made my mistakes.
Now I don't know what it's like to be you.
You don't know what it's like to be me.
I don't know what it's like to be me.